<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prophecyes of the incomparable Dr. Martin Luther concerning the downfall of the Pope of Rome, and the subversion of the German Empire, to be over-run by the armies of the Turks, together with the many reasons that he giveth for it : as also, the remarkable prophecy of the learned and reverend Mvscvlvs, to the same effect / collected by R.C. M.A.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23003</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12238686</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12238686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56718</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56718)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 606:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prophecyes of the incomparable Dr. Martin Luther concerning the downfall of the Pope of Rome, and the subversion of the German Empire, to be over-run by the armies of the Turks, together with the many reasons that he giveth for it : as also, the remarkable prophecy of the learned and reverend Mvscvlvs, to the same effect / collected by R.C. M.A.</title>
                  <author>R. C., M.A.</author>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 37 [i.e. 47] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Andrew Kembe, and Edward Thomas ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: prelim. p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</term>
               <term>Prophecies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56718:1"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe spirit of <hi>Luther,</hi> whereby he did Beat down the ſtrong Holds of sin, and over came both the Falſe-hood and the Pride of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the Spirit of Truth, there being as great an Antipathy betwixt Truth and Falſe-hood, as between Heaven and Hell, GOD himſelf being the Authour of Truth, and the Devil the Father of Lyes; By the ſame Spirit of Truth, by which <hi>Luther</hi> Convinced the Corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> He Compiled his <hi>Prophecies</hi> and foretold thoſe ſad Events which ſhould fall upon <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Impire of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi>
               </hi> unleſs they would for ſake their ſins, the Inviters and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers of the Wrath of God Theſe Prophecies we have here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the View, and the Readers are to take Notice that with much Induſtry and Diligence, they have been carefully Collected out of the Book of <hi>Dr. Martin Luther,</hi> Intituled <hi>Colloquia. Menſalia,</hi> which Book being of Excellent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, as may appear by the Approbation of the moſt Reverend Father in <hi>GOD,</hi> Doctor <hi>Land,</hi> Late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (as in the laſt page of this Book is ſpecified;) Is to be ſold by <hi>Andrew Kembe</hi> at Saint <hi>Margarets-Hill</hi> in <hi>South-warke;</hi> And <hi>Edward Thomas,</hi> at the sign of the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little Brittain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Book is Admirable for Inſtruction and Reproofe; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies are many, and ſome of them already Accompliſhed, as may more Largly Appear by the Book it Self, of which we have here given You but a Short View. The Reader alſo may be pleaſed to take Notice, that the two Above-mentioned Book-Sellers. have both of them to Sell, that moſt Incomperable Book of <hi>Mr. John Selden,</hi> Tranſlated into Engliſh, called <hi>Mare Clanſim,</hi> or the Interest and Propriety of His <hi>Sacred Majeſty,</hi> on the Narrow Seas.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56718:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PROPHECYES Of the Incomparable D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Martin Luther, Concerning the Downfall of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>ROME,</hi> and the Subverſion of the <hi>German EMPIRE;</hi> to be Over-run by the Armies of the <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RKS.</hi> Together with the many Reaſons that he giveth for it.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, The Remarkable Prophecy of the Learned and Reverend <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> to the ſame Effect.</p>
            <p>Collected by <hi>R. C.</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Andrew Kembe,</hi> and <hi>Edward Thomas,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops at Saint <hi>Margarets</hi> Hill in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and at the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> at Little <hi>Brittain,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56718:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56718:2"/>
            <head>The Prophecies of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> concerning the Down-fall of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire,</hi> that will be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run with the Armies of the <hi>Turks;</hi> together with the Reaſons that he giveth for it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Name of <hi>Martin Luther</hi> is ſo Famous through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all <hi>Europe,</hi> that he cannot be unknown ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Papiſt, or the Proteſtant, having deeply obliged the One, by oppoſing the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and the Falſe-hoods of the other; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, there were ſome others before Him that did write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> As <hi>John Hus, Jerome of Prague,</hi> who were the Firſt Fruits of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and were both Honoured with the Crowns of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome; Martin Luther,</hi> as he came after them, ſo having a higher Spirit to imbolden him, and a more Powerfull Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Friends to aſſiſt him, did give a greater blow to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and fulfilled his own Prophecy, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56718:3"/>was, <hi>That the longer Popery continued, the more it ſhould be every day contemned:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Luther colloquia Commo alis, <hi>page 537.</hi>
               </note> The Prophecies of this great Reformer of the Church were Remarkable, foretelling the Ruine of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the <hi>German</hi> Empire, which ſhould be brought unto Confuſion by the Formidable Powers of the <hi>Turk:</hi> But before I repreſent unto you the Prophecies of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> it will not be amiſſe to give you a ſhort View of his Life, and of the Prophecies of others concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; that ſo by reading of their Prophecies in Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to himſelf; His own Prophecies concerning the Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the <hi>German</hi> Empire may gaine the greater Confirmation.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, I ſhall give you the True Preſage of <hi>John Hilton,</hi> who was himſelf a Friar by Profeſſion; He Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied, that much about the Year, one thouſand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixteen (which was at the ſame time when <hi>Luther</hi> began to Declare himſelf againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the Myſtery of Ungodlineſs would begin to be Diſcovered, and the Son of Righteouſneſs ſhine forth in the Truth of the Goſpel, and that Popery would at that time finde in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> and in other parts of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> a general Declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; which Prophecy was by <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> who flouriſhed in thoſe times moſt undoubtedly fulfilled.</p>
            <p>But the Teſtimony of <hi>John Hus,</hi> who being condemned to ſuffer the Flames of Martyrdom at <hi>Conſtance,</hi> is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable; It was almoſt one hundred years, before that <hi>Luther</hi> did openly profeſſe himſelf an Enemy, to the Errours and Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome; John Hus</hi> being brought unto the Stake,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inthers Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquia,</hi> page 534. The Belief of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> 203.</note> expreſſed himſelf in theſe words. <hi>This day,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>you do roſt a Gooſe,</hi> (for ſo the word <hi>Hus</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies in the <hi>German</hi> Tongue) <hi>but one hundred years hence, you ſhall hear a Swan to Warble, whom you ſhall not be able to roſt nor overcome;</hi> and this at the end of the Time preſcribed was effectually made good, for then <hi>Martin Luthers</hi> voice was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually heard, who Preached ſo powerfully with his Tongue, and wrote ſo ſharply with his Pen, as not any one before him, ſince the time of the Apoſtles, did the like; and notwithſtanding all the Fury and Violence of the Papiſts,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56718:3"/>who with elabourate Malice endeavoured to ſuppreſſe him, he continued Preaching and Writing againſt them many years afterwards, and departed this Life in Peace to the Praiſe of God, and the great Shame and Deriſion of the Pope and his Accomplice: We may inſtance many other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyes of the like Nature, which we purpoſely forbear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to contract much into a little Volume.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Parentage, and Life of <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin Luther</hi> was the Son of a Farmer, he was born at <hi>Iſleben,</hi> in the County of <hi>Mansfield,</hi> in the year one thouſand foure hundred and eighty three, on the <hi>10th</hi> day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber:</hi> His Father, his Grand Father, and his Great Grand-Father (as he ſaith himſelf) were Farmers; His Father abandoning his Farme upon ſome diſcontents, and finding ſome Profitable Imployments at <hi>Mansfield,</hi> he addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to that place, where he was one of the Miners in the Silver Mines; In the mean time <hi>Luther</hi> had his Education in the ſame Town where he was born, and being fitted for the Univerſity at <hi>Erſurd,</hi> he took there the Degrees of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chellour, and Maſter of Arts, and in a ſhort proceſſe of time, he took upon him the Habit and Formality of a Friar, at which his Father was much diſpleaſed; But it pleaſed God by this means to make uſe of him for the over-throwing of the Power of Antichriſt; <hi>Luther</hi> having found how direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite the Supremacy of the Pope was to the Doctrine of the primitive times, there grew on it the firſt contention, which being bandyed up and down with Animoſity, it gave <hi>Luther</hi> the occaſion more ſtrictly to examine ſome other Corruptions in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which he did with ſo much vigour, that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>13th,</hi> underſtanding what great hurt and prejudice he received from it, and fearing it might bring a further Contempt upon him, he did exaſperate <hi>Rodolphus</hi> the ſecond, at that time Empire, that all the Books of <hi>Martin Luther</hi> ſhould be burned, and that it ſhould be Death for any man to keep them in his Houſe, which Edict was not onely ſuddainly put in Execution by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56718:4"/>himſelf, but it was continued alſo by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, who was a ſevere Enemy, and a Perſecutor of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther,</hi> long before this had Eſponſed a Virgin, whoſe Name was <hi>Katherine Bora,</hi> ſhe had ſometimes entred hen ſelf into a Cloyſter of the Nuns, but diſliking many abuſes ſhe found therein, before her year of Probation was expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe relinquiſhed it.</p>
               <p>This gave an occaſion to the Monks and Friars to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime againſt <hi>Luther</hi> as having broken the Vow of Chaſtity;<note place="margin">Luthers Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loqua. <hi>445.</hi>
                  </note> but <hi>Luther</hi> had abandoned the Office of a Friar before; nevertheleſſe he thus far declared himſelf, <hi>That a Preacher of the Goſpel being orderly called thereunto, ought above all. things to purify himſelf before he teacheth others, and if he be able with a good Conſcience to live unmarried, it is his ſafeſt courſe to continue ſo, but in caſe he cannot abſtain, and live chaſtly, he is then to marry, and to take a wife, for God hath provided ſuch a Remedy for that Infirmity;</hi> I could here inſert <hi>Luther</hi>'s own Prayer before his Marriage,<note place="margin">Vide Luth. colloq. <hi>452.</hi>
                  </note> and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he took a Wife, which was, as he himſelf ſaid to upbraid the Devil, and to confound the filthy incontinent life in Popery, which was ſo odious and abominable, that Pope <hi>Leo</hi> himſelf was taken out of the World at that time when he was committing Buggery with a Proſtituted Boy. I could here alſo inſert the lamentable Fruits of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married Life in Prieſts and Nuns, which have been ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that not onely in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> but in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> alſo, and many other Places, there have been found in Ponds and Cellars many thouſand heads of Infants, who thus deſperately have been thrown away to preſerve the Reputation of the Chaſtity of the Nuns and Friars: But I muſt returne from whence a little I have digreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi>'s Name growing Famous in <hi>Germany,</hi> for the great overthrows which he gave to many of the chiefeſt Profeſſors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to the Supremacy of the Pope himſelf, he was ſummoned by the Emperour to appear at the Imperial Diet at <hi>Worms,</hi> which when the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56718:4"/>Prince <hi>Electour</hi> of <hi>Saxony</hi> underſtood, he did earneſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him from it, alleaging that he ſhould have the whole Chriſtian world againſt him; and although he was ready and willing to defend him, yet <hi>Luther</hi> and he being but two perſons, they were unable to oppoſe ſo great a Multitude; he there adviſed him not to undertake ſo dangerous a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but to be warned by the example of <hi>John Hus;</hi> who although he had the Emperours Letters of ſafe Conduct to preſerve him, yet he was ſurprized there, and conſumed by fire to aſhes. <hi>Luther</hi> having heard the Elector to give him this council, made anſwer to him, that he muſt confeſſe,<note place="margin">Luthers Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loqu. <hi>433.</hi>
                  </note> that (as the caſe now ſtood) he was too weak to defend him; nevertheleſſe he was reſolved to go, and to defend the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor; for although (ſaid he) there be in <hi>Worms</hi> as many Devils as there be Tiles on all the Houſes of the City; yet I am reſolved to go thither, and to maintain what I have done and undertaken.</p>
               <p>Many more ſuch examples may be given of his Courage, and his Confidence; at the laſt when he ſaw that by his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours the Goſpel began to flouriſh and to be preached not onely in <hi>Germany</hi> but other Countryes, and that he had reaped the comfert of his Induſtry and his Study it pleaſed God to viſite him with ſickneſſe, at which time, giving thanks unto God who had delivered him from ſo many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and Aſſaults of his Mercileſs Enemies, he compoſed theſe following Verſes in Latine.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Quaeſitus toties, toties tibi <hi>Roma</hi> petitus,</l>
                  <l>Ille ego per Chriſtum vivo <hi>Lutherus</hi> adhuc,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na mihi ſpes eſt quâ non fraudabor Jeſus,</l>
                  <l>Hunc mihi dum teneam perfida <hi>Roma</hi> cave.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Which are thus in Engliſh,
<q xml:lang="eng">
                     <l>Behold! through Chriſt, I <hi>Luther</hi> yet do live,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Rome</hi> ſo often ſought, but I believe</l>
                     <l>Chriſt Jeſus is my onely hope, by whom,</l>
                     <l>Whileſt I do live, take heed perfidious <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56718:5"/>
               <p>Being a little recovered, he was adviſed to take the Ayre which accordingly he did,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luthers</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy on his own Death</note> on the ſixteenth of <hi>February</hi> in the year, 1546. at what time, he ſaid, when I come again to <hi>Wittembergh,</hi> I will be lodged in a Coffin, and will ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render to the Worms a ſat <hi>Luther</hi> to feed upon, and ſo it fell out; for two days afterwards he was tranſlated from this life unto a better, and perceiving himſelf to grow fainter and draw near unto his end, he called for Pen, Inke, and Paper, and wrote this verſe following to lye as it were an Epitaph upon his own Tomb.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Peſtis eram viven, moriens ero mors tua Papa.</l>
               </q>
               <q xml:lang="eng">
                  <l>Living, I was a Plague to thee,</l>
                  <l>Dying, O! Pope thy Death I'le be.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Which by <hi>Philip Melancthon</hi> was rendred in a Diſtich much after the ſame ſence, and manner.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Quidum vixit erat tua peſtis (Papa) <hi>Lutherus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hic tibi cauſa, ſuo funere, mortis erit.</l>
               </q>
               <q xml:lang="eng">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luther</hi> who living was thy Plague, he ſhall,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe by his death, O Pope! thy utter fall.</l>
               </q>
               <p>He lived ſixty and three years, and was buried at <hi>Iſleben</hi> (where he was born) on the 19th. of <hi>February</hi> 1546. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given you this Account of his life, we ſhall now paſſe unto his Prophecyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Prophecies of <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And above all,<note place="margin">His Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy concein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Turk</hi> page, 518.</note> this is moſt remarkable; The <hi>Turk,</hi> ſaith he, ſhall give a great Clap to <hi>Germany;</hi> Me thinks I ſee him Marching through and through the whole Body of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; who ſo liveth one hundred years and upwards, will ſee the ſame accompliſhed, I oftentimes do contemplate thereupon, and thinking on the great miſery which will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue upon the Empire, I do ſweat thereat; Nevertheleſſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56718:5"/>
                  <hi>Germany</hi> goeth on in ſin, and refuſeth to be helped: No hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane power or potentate can beat the <hi>Turk,</hi> but onely that Man who is named Chriſt; as for the Emperour, King <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimand</hi> and the Princes, they can accompliſh nothing.</p>
               <p>It is obſervable, that although <hi>Luther</hi> had Prophecied this of the <hi>Turk,</hi> yet he had no good opinion of him;<note place="margin">How the <hi>Turk</hi> mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth War and prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in it, <hi>Luthers Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq.</hi> 519.</note> for there being a great Commotion at that time in <hi>Germany</hi> concerning Religion, the <hi>Turk</hi> deſired to know what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man <hi>Luther</hi> was, and of what years: when it was told him that he was a Corpulent man, and of about fifty years of age, the <hi>Turk</hi> replyed, I could wiſh he were younger, for he ſhall have of me a gracious Lord; which when it was brought to <hi>Luthers</hi> eare by the Prince <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Saxony;</hi> God preſerve me (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) from ſuch a gracious Lord as the Emperour of <hi>Turkey</hi> is, for the <hi>Turk</hi> is a Crafty and Subtile Enemy, who maketh War not onely with great Courage,<note place="margin">The <hi>Turk</hi> able to maintain a yearly Army of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth to above 15. millions, <hi>Luth. Col.</hi> page, 5198.</note> and a Formidable Number of Souldiers, but alſo he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageth it with many Stratagems, and much Craft and Sub tilty; he is alwayes beating up the Quarters of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and by that means makes them faint and weary; he keepeth them waking with often Skirmiſhing, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ingageth with the whole Body of his Army, unleſſe he be aſſured of the Victory; He is ready to take all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages; His Power is great, being able in <hi>Luthers</hi> Time to maintain and pay yearly two hundred thouſand Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, which at the leaſt amounteth to fifteen Millions of Rix Dollars.</p>
               <p>By Degrees the <hi>Turk</hi> ſuppreſſed the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> who before were Conquerours, and Lords of all, in <hi>Syria, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and in the Land of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and hath alſo great Dominions in <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Greece:</hi> Much about thirty years before <hi>Luthers</hi> time he utterly over-threw the whole Army of the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> and killed the <hi>Soldan</hi> in that Battel.</p>
               <p>The <hi>German</hi> Princes, ſaid <hi>Luther,</hi> ought to be well Qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and Armed to incounter with ſo powerfull an Enemy as the <hi>Turks.</hi> The Princes themſelves ought in their own Perſon to advance into the field, and not encounter the <hi>Turk</hi> with any inconſiderable number, for the <hi>Turke</hi> is an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56718:6"/>Enemy that ought not to be Undervalued, or Contemned; The Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is given unto him to go againſt the Saints of God, Dan.</hi> II. And therefore his Fortunes and his Victories are ſo great: He maketh three Thrones or Seats in his Religion; In the midſt, he placeth <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> on his left Hand, and <hi>Mahomet</hi> on the right; He taketh his Oath by <hi>God</hi> who Created Heaven and Earth; by <hi>Mahomet</hi> his Servant,<note place="margin">The <hi>Turks</hi> Oath, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 520.</note> and by the Foure ſcore and foure Prophets ſent from Heaven. I am afraid (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) it will go with <hi>Germany</hi> (which is one of the beſt Countries in the World) as heretofore it went with <hi>Troy, Fuit Ilium &amp; ingens Gloria Teucrorum,</hi> ſaith the Poet; Heretofore there was a <hi>Troy,</hi> and great was the Glory of the <hi>Trojans;</hi> So here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore there was a <hi>Germany,</hi> and great was the Glory of the <hi>Germans;</hi> but now a ſhort time will ſee it brought into ſtreights and Devaſtation.</p>
               <p>The great Overthrows which the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhall give to the Forces of the Emperour,<note place="margin">The over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw which the <hi>Turks</hi> will give the Emperour foretold by the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> page 520.</note> was not onely foretold by the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) but alſo it was delivered in the Revelation of <hi>St. John;</hi> to the end that Godly and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Chriſtians ſhould not be affrighted at his great Power and Tyranny. <hi>Daniel</hi> excelleth in his Prophecies which ſhall continue to the end of the World; He moſt clearly deſcribeth the Kingdomes of Antichriſt, and the <hi>Turk,</hi> in the Revelation of <hi>St. John,</hi> Chap. 13. It is Written; <hi>That it was given unto him to make War with the Saints, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them;</hi> which words are expreſly ſpoken of the <hi>Turk,</hi> and not of the <hi>Pope;</hi> for the Saints overcome not by their Sanctity, but by their Patience, and in their overcoming by Faith, when their Bodies are Murdered: The Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> proceedeth further, and ſaith, <hi>It ſhall be for a Time, Times, and half a Time.</hi> If Time ſignifieth a Year, as peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it may, then this Prophecy was firſt of all fulfilled in <hi>Antiochus,</hi> who Tyrannized three Years and an halfe, over the Nation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after which time he miſerably rotted, and moſt lamentably died in ſuch an intolerable ſtench. oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by his Diſeaſe, that not any were able to indure the moſt noyſomeſavour of it, or to remain about him.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56718:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> would oftentimes complain of the great negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> in giving an Advantage to the <hi>Turk</hi> alwayes to overcome him, and to taxe in one Town after another; whereas the Emperour ſhould alwaies have kept a Gallant and a Reſolute Army in the Field, or to have them in a readineſſe in their Winter Quarters to be drawn forth into the Field upon the Emergencies of any Advantage or Oppoſition, for this is the vigilant Cuſtome of the Turks in all his Enterpriſes, whoſe <hi>Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>izaries</hi> (the moſt Reſolute and moſt Experienced of all his Souldiers, are always ready at the beat of a Drum for any Enterprize.) <hi>Mahomet</hi> began to Appear in the World in the Year, Six hundred and thirty, after the Incarnation of our Saviour, which is now above one thouſand years agoe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) do ſwell as much with their Lies, as with their Victories, they acknowledge that <hi>Iſaac</hi> was the firſt and the True Son of the Promiſe; but when he ſhould be Sacriſiced, he conveyed himſelf away from his Fathers ſight, pretending that he would go and fetch a Knife, and other Utenſils for the Sacrifice; whereupon <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> came, and of his own Accord did offer up himſelf to be Sacriſiced; upon which Account he became the Child of the Promiſe; This (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) is as groſſe a lye, as that of the Papiſts concerning the Adminiſtration, only under one kind in the Sacrament. And as <hi>Antiochus</hi> above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, was ſtruck by God with a loathſome Diſeaſe, and killed without hands; Even ſo (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) ſhall it go with the Pope; He ſhall fall and be deſtroyed without any Blow of the sword, or without any Hands to mannage a Sword; he ſhall Famiſh himſelf, for he hath never uſed any great or powerfull Armies whereby to Defend or Inlarge his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,<note place="margin">The Pope to fall without any blow of the Sword, <hi>Luther,</hi> pag, 520.</note> but hath ſubſiſted onely by Lying and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and pretended Scripture to maintain him in his Falſhoods, as in one place, <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> and in another, <hi>Feed my Lambs;</hi> Upon ſuch deceitful grounds he hath In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and ſo ſhall he fall again; Therefore this Prophecy in the Scriptures, <hi>He ſhall fall without Power</hi> belongeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to the Pope; For all other Potentates and Tyrants
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56718:7"/>proceed, with Power and Force; Nevertheleſſe this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) in ſome manner may reflect as well upon the <hi>Turk</hi> as upon the Pope, for they began both of them almoſt at one time under the Emperour <hi>Phocas,</hi> for then <hi>Mahomet</hi> began to ſhow his Blaſphemous Tongue, and the Pope to Rule Spititually; But the Popes Temporall Kingdome (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) hath ſcarce continued three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years, ſince he began to Rule over Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Luthers</hi> Admonition to the <hi>Germans,</hi> how they ought to make War againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ther</hi> underſtanding that the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> had ſent eighteen thouſand. <hi>Spaniards</hi> into <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to defend the ſame againſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> He ſighed, and ſaid, <hi>Theſe are ſtrange Deſigns, when the</hi> Spaniards <hi>ſhall come to defend the</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</p>
               <p>The Greateſt part of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Adjacent to them are <hi>Moorans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luthers Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq. <hi>p. 521.</hi>
                  </note> Baptized Jews, that believe in nothing at all; Hereupon <hi>Luther</hi> wrote a Letter to the <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of the Emperours Army, at that time in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> diligently admoniſhing him to conſider that he had four Great Enemies to Encounter with:
<list>
                     <item>The firſt, was with the Devil:</item>
                     <item>The ſecond, with the Turk:</item>
                     <item>The third, with Gods Wrath:</item>
                     <item>And the fourth, with the Sins of that Nation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>He told him that all the Kingdomes of the Earth had Fallen, and been Deſtroyed by Home-bred Diſſentions; So fell the Empires of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians; So</hi> fell the Empires of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans;</hi> and ſo likewiſe will it go with <hi>Germany,</hi> ſaid <hi>Luther;</hi> For the Princes of the Empire will not Agree amongſt Themſelves; And ſo at laſt will it go with the <hi>Turk</hi> himſelf, for the Higher he climbeth,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56718:7"/>he is in the greater Danger to Fall; When his Time commeth, then it will be done in a Moment, and the Lord God will lay his Kingdome in the Aſhes.</p>
               <p>I made mention in the Life of <hi>Luther,</hi> that ſome Eminent Perſons preſaged of his Birth, and what a Scourge he ſhould prove to the Licentious Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year one thouſand five hundred and eleven, a Capuchin Friar (in the preſence of Doctor <hi>Staupits,</hi> and divers others at <hi>Rome</hi>) related a Dream, which on the night before he had Dreamed; which was, <hi>That a Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite ſhould ariſe under Pope</hi> Leo <hi>the tenth, and ſhould be a bitter Enemy to tho Church of</hi> Rome; Whereupon <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthou</hi> ſaid, <hi>This Hermite is</hi> Luther, for the <hi>Auſtine</hi> Friars were called Hermites. When many years afterwards, I was at <hi>Rome</hi> (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) they ſhewed me for a precious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique the Halter wherewith <hi>Judas</hi> hanged himſelf, which ought not by me (ſaid he) to be forgotten, to ſhew in what a thick darkneſſe of Ignorance our Fore-Fathers lived; <hi>Rome</hi> was once a Holy City, but now ſhe is the Spouſe of the Devil, and the Enemy of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> Diſcourſing of the Fathers of the Church; <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> (ſaid he) was the Chiefeſt and the Eldeſt; after him <hi>St. Jerome;</hi> next unto him <hi>St. Auguſtine;</hi> and after him <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourth: I have ſeen <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) painted in ſome Books like a Friar with a Hood, by which that Holy Man was much injured, for he lived a publique kind of life, like a Common Citizen, he uſed Silver Spoones and Cupps; he lived in ordinary amongſt the people, and converſed with them, he lived no ſuch Monkiſh kind of life, as the Papiſts have feigned of him. The Old Fathers taught better,<note place="margin">The Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations in Religion brought in by the Pope <hi>Luther,</hi> p. 350.</note> and with a greater power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe then they Wrote. After the Fathers, came the Pope, and fell in with his miſchievous Traditions, and humane Ordinances, and like a Deluge that beareth all before it, he over-flowed the Church, and inſnared the Conſciences touching the eating of Meats, and concerning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56718:8"/>Maſſes, and Friars Hoods, and Impertinent and Prophane Decrees and Laws, inſomuch that he daily induced and brought in Abominable Errours into the Church of Chriſt, and to ſerve his own turn, perverted the Holy Scripture, and either expunged many things that were Written directly againſt him in the Fathers, or elſe did interpret them to that ſence which might ſerve beſt for his own Advantage; Inſomuch, that upon theſe and ſome other Conſiderations like unto them, <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Compoſed a little Tract, of the birth and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Deſolation of Antichriſt, which becauſe he tooke ſome paynes in the Forming of the Extract, I have in this place inſerted it, hoping that you will receive ſome pleaſure in the Reading of it.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="tract">
                           <p>The Devil begat Darkneſſe; Darkneſſe begat Ignorance; Ignorance begat Errour, and his Brethren: Errour begat Free-will, and Preſumption out of Self conceit; Free-will begat Merit; Merit begat Forgetfulneſſe of God; Forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe begat Tranſgreſſion; Tranſgreſſion begat Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; Superstition begat Satisfaction; Satisfaction begat the Oblation of the Maſſe; The Oblation of the Maſs, begat <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction begat the Prieſt; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat Misbelief; Misbelief begat Hypocriſie; Hypocriſie begat trading with Offerings for Gain; Trading begat Purgatory; Purgatory begat the Yearly Solemne Vigils; The Yearly Vigils begat Church-Livings; Church-Livings begat Mammon; Mammon begat Superfluity; Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity begat Exceſſe; Exceſſe begat Rage; Rage begat Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe; Licentiouſneſſe begat Dominion; Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion begat Pomp; Pomp begat Ambition; Ambition begat Symony; Symony begat the Pope and his Brethren; The Pope begat the Myſtery of Iniquity; the Mystery of Iniquity begat Sophistical Divinity; Sophiſtical Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56718:8"/>begat the Rejecting of the Holy Scripture; the Rejecting ef the Holy Scripture, begat Tyranny; Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny begat the Murdering of the Saints; the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Saints begat the Contempt of God; the Contempt of God begat Diſpenſation; Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion begat Wilfull Sin; Wilfull Sin, begat Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; Abomination begat Deſolation; Deſolation begat Anguiſh; Anguiſh begat Questioning; Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioning begat the ſearching out of the Grounds of Truth; out of which the Pope, called Antichriſt, is Revealed.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Thus have you out of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> in his own words, the Genealogy of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and by what a concatenated Race this Myſtery of Iniquity came to be Revealed; the time will come ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4. <hi>When they will not endure ſound Doctrine, but after their own Luſts they will heap unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Teachers; having itching ears, and they ſhall turn away their ears from hearing of the Truth, and ſhall be turned into Fables.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But amongſt all the Fables, and Idolatries in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> there is none more Remarkable then the Maſſe; <hi>Luther</hi> in his Tract hereof declareth,<note place="margin">Luther Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq. <hi>330.</hi>
                  </note> that no Tongue is able to expreſſe the Abominations of the Maſſe, neither can the Heart of man comprehend the ſame; and he ſaith it were no wonder, if that God ſhould deſtroy the World for the Maſſe-ſake, and the Abominations therein committed with Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven.</p>
               <p>When I was a young Friar (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) at <hi>Ertfurd,</hi> and was conſtrained to go out into the Vilages For Puddings and Cheeſes, I came to a little Town where I heard Maſſe; now when I had put on my Veſtments and my Ornaments, and made my approaches to the Altar, the Sexton of the Church began merrily to play upon the Lute, at which I could hardly forbear from Laughing, for I was unaccuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſuch Muſick.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56718:9"/>
               <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> muſt fall, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> and Popery with him, for it is the Devil himſelf, and all manner of Blaſphemy to hold the ſinal cauſe of the inſtitution of humane Traditions to be the true Service and Worſhip of God and that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation;<note place="margin">One cauſe of the fall of the Pope and Popery. page, 328.</note> and this Aſſertion is moſt monſtrous, for ſuppoſe ſuch humane Traditions were the beſt and moſt eſteemed works of Chriſtianity, which they are not, yet to affirm that they are neceſſary to Salvation, or do give God any ſatisfaction for ſin, and that by that means they do purchaſe Grace, is to make our beſt works to be of God utterly rejected. Wherefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>In vain do they ſerve me, teaching ſuch Doctrines which are the Commandements of Men;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If either we, or any Angel from Heaven preach any other Doctrine to you then that which we have preached, let him be accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Antichriſt muſt fall, and it plainly and clearly appeareth, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pope true Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and muſt fall, page, 312.</note> that the Pope is true Antichriſt; thoſe that tranſgreſſe his Decrees and Statutes, are farr more ſeverely and diligently puniſhed, then thoſe who offend the Laws and the word of God: In ſuch a ſort doth the Pope exalt himſelf over, and above God, and he is therefore moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called Antichriſt, in regard that he ſitteth in the Temple, and in the Church of God, and boaſteth himſelf above all that is called God. The <hi>Turk</hi> is not this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> for the ſitteth not in Gods Church; he is but the Battle-Axe of God, whereby he executeth his Vengeance upon the Nations, he is a wicked Beaſt; out of Gods Church, there is no Antichriſt; now the Pope ſitteth in the Holy Church, and taketh unto him that Honour and Worſhip which is due unto God onely, therefore the Pope muſt be the true Antichriſt. It is but a cold, and an idle dream of the Papiſts, that Antichriſt ſhould be a ſingle, and an unattended perſon that ſhould govern in a wilde way by ſuborning, and ſcattering of moneys in the ſtreets, and that he ſhould do Minacles, and carry about him a fiery O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and that he ſhould deſtroy the Saints, <hi>Eliah,</hi> and <hi>Enoch.</hi> There are too many (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) who complain and think,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56718:9"/>I am too fierce and too violent againſt the Pope, when alas I conceive my ſelf to be too milde; I do wiſh that I could breath out thunder-bolts againſt the Pope and Popery, and that every word were a clap of Thunder.</p>
               <p>I do believe, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> that the Pope out oſſpecial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, ordained and appointed the Feaſts of St. <hi>Silve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and of St. <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to be Celebrated eight days after the Nativity of our Saviour, in regard that St. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> brought unto the Pope the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> and St. <hi>Silveſter</hi> the Empire of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the year one thouſand five hundred and thirty, in the Raign of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth; the Pope endeavoured by money to corrupt ſome of the Kings Counſellours; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed one of them who was of the Blood-Royal, and near unto the Kings Perſon, that he would give that Kingdom unto him.<note place="margin">The Pope boaſted in <hi>Luthers</hi> days that he was Heir to the Kingdome of <hi>England.;</hi> page, 310.</note> The Pope boaſted that he himſelf was Heir un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Kingdome, by reaſon it was held as from him <hi>per feodum,</hi> but the Popes pride is ſo great, that he muſt fall; and it is no great wonder (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) that even in his time, the Majeſty of the Pope was already fallen. All Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, Emperours, Kings, and Princes before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, did ever tremble at the Majeſty and the Power of the Pope, none durſt mutter ſo much as one word againſt him. This great god is now fallen, his own creatures the Monks and Fryers do begin to be his Enemies, and they onely adhear unto him for their Lucres ſake.</p>
               <p>Popery muſt needs be brought to the ſtake and pay for all; the Pope ſhall be devoured by Monks and Friers, which are his own Vermine and Creatures; It is they who do ſhake and make looſe the faireſt Monarchy of Popery, which with great Advice and Conſideration was erected. He hath forbidden them to enter into the State of Matrimony, when notwithſtanding he hath commanded the ſame to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a Sacrament; but if Matrimony be a Sacrament, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> then it cannot be obſerved by the Heathen; for the Unbelieving <hi>Gentiles</hi> who are the Heathen, have nothing to doe with the Sacraments.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56718:10"/>
               <p>The Pope (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) muſt and ſhall fall;<note place="margin">Another Reaſon of the Popes Fall.</note> the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Papiſts is great and horrible, and is much to be admired, becauſe in the Reconciliation for the living and the (and though they would pretend it is a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice of Thankſgiving) yet all their Cannoniſts and School-Divines, and their Preachers in their Pulpits do apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſprove it; you may obſerve the impudence of ſome Popelins, that go about to prove this horrible Errour; every Lievetenant ſay they, hath the ſame full and compleat power as his Lord and Maſter: <hi>Peter</hi> was Chriſts Lievete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, therefore he hath the ſame power that Chriſt had; and becauſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>To me is given all power in Heaven, and in Earth;</hi> therefore they conclude, that the Pope who is <hi>Peters</hi> Lievetenant, hath the ſame Power as Chriſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Luther</hi> anſwers, That ſuppoſe it be granted, that <hi>Peter</hi> was Chriſts Lievetenant here on Earth, ſo long as he demeaned himſelf according to Chriſts word? yet it doth not hereupon follow, that <hi>Peter</hi> is Chriſts Lievete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Heaven; for Chriſt that ſaid unto him, <hi>what thou bindeſt on Earth,</hi> doth not ſay unto him, what thou ſhalt binde in Heaven. He ſaith unto <hi>Peter, follow me, feed my ſheep,</hi> my kingdome is not of this World; that is to ſay, it is not gotten by humane ſtrength and power, neither will it be maintained thereby.</p>
               <p>The Pope therefore (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) is a Right <hi>Jew,</hi> who boaſteth to enjoy by Chriſt a temporal Kingdome, he alone will have all the Power &amp; Authority, he will Rule and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine all Councels, and Encroach upon them under the Name of God; If one ſhould have defloured the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or have cruciſied Chriſt; yet the Pope for money could pardon and forgive the ſame; therefore his Dominion is but ſhort,<note place="margin">Page, 306.</note> and will be brought to Confuſion in the year, 666. according to the Number of the Beaſt, in the thirteenth Chapter of the <hi>Revelations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, Popedome (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) muſt fall;<note place="margin">Another reaſon of the Popes Fall.</note> It hath been alwayes managed by wicked perſons, and Correſpondent to their Doctrine; for as the Creator is, ſuch is alſo his Creature.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56718:10"/>Pope <hi>Alezander</hi> was a Moran, that is to ſay a Baptiſed <hi>Jew,</hi> he believed nothing at all; he had a Concubine called <hi>Lucretia,</hi> to whom he afterwards eſpouſed his own Pon: the Pope that ſucceeded him was ſo great an enemy to him, that he cauſed all the Gates, Doors, and Windows on which his Name was Written, or his Armes Pourtrayed, to be broken down and defaced; when God ſpeaketh the word <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> fall; <hi>Rome</hi> be deſtroyed and lye in the Aſhes, Pope come down from your Throne, the word of God will be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, and muſt be accompliſhed immediately.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond,<note place="margin">Page 302.</note> celebrated a faire Maſſe to the Devil upon <hi>Eaſter</hi> day in the morning, at which time he made a lamentable Slaughter, and Maſſacre with the <hi>French,</hi> in which twenty thouſand Chriſtians were ſlain. The Pope and his accomplices (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) ſtrive not for the benefit or the advancement of the Church, but onely to purchaſe Wealth, and to overcome Kingdomes and Countries. Therefore the Legal and Juſt proceedings of God, will fall upon the Pope and his Retinue, as already it hath begun; for againſt him, the three firſt Petitions in the Lords Prayer may juſtly be inverted; Blaſphemed and Accurſed be the name of the Pope, his Kingdome be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and thrown down, his will be diſappointed and confounded; I hope (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) the numbers of his Fryers and of his Nuns ſhall no more increaſe, when the Popes feet are chopt off, then he muſt creep,<note place="margin">Page, 307;</note> for he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand long as he now ſtandeth.</p>
               <p>Again the Pope muſt fall, for he can neither be Primate, nor chief Head in Chriſtendome, and no ways poſſibly can viſite and govern all the Churches, no not although he were <hi>Elias, Eliſha, Peter</hi> or <hi>Paul. Meloncthon</hi> put a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to <hi>Luther,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>In caſe the Emperour ſhould give over all his Right and Intereſt to the Pope, whether ought we to ſhew obedience to the Pope or not?</hi> Whereupon <hi>Luther</hi> replyed, <hi>The Emperour as an ordained Governour, hath no power to reſign over his Intereſts to the Pope who is no Magiſt are nor Governour;</hi> For the Pope is a thing which ſtandeth upon no ground,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56718:11"/>neither could it be called a Reſignation to turn over the Emperours Right, and Titles to the Pope, but it would be rather a Devaſtation whereby the Empire would be leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and extenuated. The Emperour hath neither Right nor Power to do it, for the Empire is not his own; it is not Succeſſive but Elective. To conclude, when it is denyed that the Pope is a Governour (as in truth he is not) then is he bereaved of all, for whatſoever he hath, he hath it not by Right, but hath Stolen and uſurped it. When it is ſpoken; therefore that the Emperour received the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the Pope,<note place="margin">Page, 309.</note> it is of no valve, for he could never give that which he never had; And it is a meer Fable, that either <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour, or <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, gave to the Pope ſuch great Poſſeſſions as is boaſted off; It was the Avarice of the Popes, and not any great Donations of the Emperours, by which the Popes have acquired ſuch great Poſſeſſions; In former times the Popes were not Lords over Emperours and Kings, but the Popes were inſtituted and ordained by Emperours.</p>
               <p>Pride again muſt have a fall, and ſo undoubtedly muſt the Pope; The Pope in one day (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) made thirty Cardinalls, which on the other ſide of the River of <hi>Tiber</hi> were Mett and Received by a gallant Body of Horſe, whereat, all the Cannons in the City of <hi>Rome</hi> were diſcharged, and the Acclamations and the Joyes of the People did ſtrive to out-voice the Thunders of the Cannons; at the laſt the Pope himſelf came into the Field, at which the Great Guns in <hi>Rome</hi> were all diſcharged; and what with the noyſe of the Cannons, and the hurry of the People; the Confuſion begat a Terrour and a Trepida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was ſo great in the City, that the Temples alſo were ſenſible of it; inſomuch, that in one of the Churches, the Child fell out of the armes of the Bleſſed Virgin; and (if we may believe Paſquil) he aſcended up into heaven, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that amongſt the reſt, he alſo ſhould be made a Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. On the ſame day and at the ſame time, a Prieſt ſaying Maſſe at the Altar, did drop the conſecrated Hoſt, and for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56718:11"/>fear ſpilled the Cup, which being brought on the next day to the care of the Pope; he ſaid, that one of thoſe whom he had Created a Cardinall, would prove a Plague to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which not long afterwards, did fall out accordingly: not long afterward the Goſpel began to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed again, and brought to light by the Pen, and by the Preaching of <hi>Martin Luther;</hi> ſome time after that when the Poſitions of <hi>Martin Luther</hi> concerning the Popes Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, were brought unto the Pope: He ſaid, <hi>A Drunken</hi> Dutch man <hi>wrote them, and when be hath taken a good Nap, and is ſober again he will then be of another minde?</hi> no more did he valve that Blow from <hi>Luthers</hi> Hand, which hath made his Chaire to totter ever ſince.</p>
               <p>I would willingly (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) fall upon the Popes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Canons; no name or ſtile, is bad enough for him, his Wickedneſſe cannot be Sounded or Expreſſed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt in one word ſheweth it, and calleth him an <hi>Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Deſſolation that ſtandeth on the Holy Mount.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> nameth him, <hi>An Oppoſer or Adverſary, that exalteth himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that is called God. Daniel</hi> alſo Prophecyeth the ſame, and ſaith, <hi>He ſhall be proud, and not regard the God of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope &amp; his accomplices relying on their great Power,<note place="margin">The Pope falling in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, p. 314.</note> and preſumption that they ſhal never fal; do thereby Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found themſelves: the Idolatry and Superſtition in Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, had for a time great Power and Operation; For <hi>Daniel</hi> touching Antichriſt ſaid, <hi>And he ſhall proſper till the Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is now near accompliſhed, for the Pope in Gods good time will moſt undoubtedly fall;</hi> God will overthrow him, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, if our own Secureneſs, and the contempt of Gods Word doth give no hinderance to it. Let us pray, that even the ſame misfortune may light upon Their Heads, which They intend ogainſt Us, and that They may fall into that Pit, which They have digged for Us. We have humbled our ſelves and ſuffered enough; They have Burned, Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Drowned and Baniſhed thoſe that were amongſt Us. They will no wayes ſuffer themſelves to be recalled from their Deviliſh Practiſes.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56718:12"/>
               <p>But we have one Remedy, Chriſt Jeſus, the Son of GOD, and of the Bleſſed Virgin; It is he who is by GOD Annointed King; He will, and ſhall ſtand faſt to defend his own Cauſe in ſpite of all Oppoſition; He hath Overcome and Deſtroyed many Great Kings, and laid them in the Duſt; For my part I will hold with Him, and fight under his Banners, rather then joyn with the <hi>Turk,</hi> with the Emperour, or the whole Univerſall World; The ſighes of GODS People do cry up unto Heaven againſt the Pope, as Jeſus the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſaith; <hi>The Tears of the Deſtreſſed do fall downwards, yet nevertheleſs they do aſcend upwards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Reaſon, and a Great one too, of the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Fall of the Pope is,<note place="margin">Page, 319.</note> the wilfull and obſtinate Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on which the very Foundation of Popery is laid, and the wicked Superſtition reared; I know not what (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) to think of it, but onely by the words of <hi>St. Paul.</hi> where he ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe they Received not the love of the Truth that they may be Saved;</hi> GOD will ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhall believe a Lye: The Pope hath two Pillars, on which the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of his ſtrength doth lean; The one is, <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you ſhall bind on Earth, the ſame alſo ſhall be bound in Heaven;</hi> And the other, the command which our Saviour gave to <hi>Peter, Feed my Sheep.</hi> Theſe two Sentences, the Pope hath wreſted ſo far, that thereby he aſſumeth the Authority and Confidence to Govern, and Mannage all things in the Church, and not in the Church onely; but in Temporall Governments alſo, according to his own will and pleaſure; Upon this account he hath altered both the Form and Subſtance of the True Doctrine, he hath damned, and ſaved whom he pleaſed. He hath depoſed Emperours, Kings, and Princes; as if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour when he ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever you bind, or whatſoever you looſe,</hi> had confined the ſence and interpretation of thoſe words onely to a Temporal Jurisdiction, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed moſt properly belongeth, to broken and to contrite
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56718:12"/>Spirits, and to the Doctrine of Faith. The Decretalls of the Pope alſo are full of Errours and of Tyranny, in which the Pope deprived of all ſhame, ſpeaketh in this manner, <hi>Non eſt praeſumendum quod upex tantae Celſitudinis erraro poſſit;</hi> It is not to be preſumed that the top of ſo great a Highneſs can erre: In this the Decretalls make half a GOD of the Pope; Amongſt whoſe Canons alſo it is to be Read, <hi>Quod Authoritas Sacrae Scripturae pendeat a Sede Romana,</hi> which is, That the Authority of the Holy Scripture doth depend on the Sea of <hi>Rome;</hi> Now when the Pope had perſuaded the people to believe this, he made them afterwards believe what he himſelf pleaſed, and brought it ſo far, that a Chriſtian denyed the Merits of the Blood of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and put on the Hood of a Friar ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein his Salvation.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luther,</hi> pa. 319.</note> This was ſuch an abominable Fall, and an Apoſtacy (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) that had it bin done by a Heathen it had been too much: Theſe powerful Errours ſuffered no man to come to the Knowledge of the Truth, as <hi>Daniel</hi> prophecied concerning the ſame; <hi>Erit Tempus quo proſternetur Veritas;</hi> A Time there will be, when Truth ſhall be trod under feet. The Infidelity and Superſtition of the Jewes is not ſo great as the Popes, for they maintained their Worſhip by the Law of God, although but ſuperſticiouſly and unbelievingly they underſtood it; But the Pope pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth directly againſt GODS Word, and treadeth on the ſame with his feet, for which he ſhall be trod upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the feet of the Indignation of GOD, he ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and be ſeen no more.</p>
               <p>The Kingdome of Chriſt, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Kingdoms of Chriſt, and of the Pope, and the Turk, p. 322.</note> is a Kingdome of Mercy, of Grace and Happineſſe. The Kingdome of the Pope is Lyes and Damnation; The Kingdome of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met is a Kingdome of Revenge, of Wrath and Devaſtation; The Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall know no end, but will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for evermore; The Kingdome of the Pope, is a Kingdome of Incontinency, as well of Lyes, and will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly come unto perdition with the Children of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. A Reformation being lately made at <hi>Wortzburgh</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:56718:13"/>amongſt the Divines, they were conſtrained to put away the Maiden and the Woman Cooks, which continued but for a Fortnight, for the Prebends did find the inconvenience ſo great, that they had leave to take them and to receive them again; But the Woman-Cooks refuſed to live with the Precends unleſs they would take and defend them, as if they were their own Wives; whereupon they took them on ſuch Conditions, and were Apparelled in ſuch a Habit, that they might not be known. I have heard (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) a Lock-Smith ſay, that for the ſpace of a fortnight, day, and night he had work enough to do in making Keyes for them, for every one of theſe Women would have a Key to her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends Chamber,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luther,</hi> page 322.</note> becauſe formerly they put them away as their Whores, but now they took them as their Wives again. Such wicked wretches muſt Popery have for her Rulers and her Governours.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, there were two <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Friars in a Monaſtry, who being much troubled to obſerve the Errours, Idolatries, and Voluptuous lives of their Aſſociates, did in their Sermons preach againſt them, and mentioned, with all, ſome particulars againſt the Pope himſelf; But in the Night time two ſecret Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers we ſent to diſpatch them, who firſt cut off their Heads and then pulled out their Tongues, and ſtuck them in their Fundaments; for ſuch Murthers, Idolatryes, and Higheſt Prophaneneſſe, God is at Enmity with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and will undoubtedly bring it to Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>If I had not been a Schollar (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) I could never have given ſuch a Fall to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for Satan had made me work enough, it was no eaſie Task for me to ſubvert, and to alter the whole Religion of Popery, which was ſo deeply rooted; but I promiſed, and did ſwear in Baptiſme, that I would cleave faſt to Chriſt and his Word, and that ſteadfaſtly I would believe in Him, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly renounce the Devil and all his Works; This Oath I renewed in all my Tribulations, without which they had overwhelmed and made an end of me; In ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56718:13"/>I could willingly have ſhewed Obedience to the Biſhops, but they would have had me roundly to deny Chriſt, make God a Lyer, and ſay the Goſpel is Hereſie.</p>
               <p>The firſt blow that <hi>Luther</hi> gave to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was by the Oppoſitions to the Poſitions of that great Papiſt <hi>Tecelius,</hi> in which <hi>Tecelius</hi> was ſo prophanely bold, as to compare the Pope with <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Croſſe Erected by the Pope to the Croſſe of Chriſt; Theſe Aſſertions (amongſt many others of the like Nature) being brought to <hi>Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> they were burned by the Students in the Market place, of which <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf giveth this Account to a Friend of his in theſe words; The Students in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, being extreamly weary of their old courſe of Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and moſt deſirous of the Sacred Bible, out of their love to me they came unto <hi>Tecelius,</hi> and made themſelves merry with him, and ſome of them being more violent then the reſt, demanded of him how he dared to bring thither ſuch paultry and chaffy ſtuffe; At the laſt, they took the Poſitions from him, and publickly burned them in the Market Place about two of the Clock in the afternoon. All this (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) was immediately known to the Prince, the Senate, and Rector, and to all of Us. This great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury done, did much diſpleaſe me, and although I am blameleſs, yet I fear the whole proceeding will be laid to my Charge.</p>
               <p>After this <hi>Johannes Hogoſtratus,</hi> a Dominican Friar wrote bitterly againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> and did excite the Pope to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute <hi>Luther</hi> with more violence, and to uſe with him the rounder Courſe of Fire and Fagot, whereupon <hi>Luther</hi> not long afterwards Addreſſed himſelf to <hi>Hidelbergh,</hi> and in the Colledge of the <hi>Auguſtinians,</hi> now called the Colledge of <hi>Sapience,</hi> he Diſputed about Juſtification by Faith; The Learned <hi>Bucer</hi> was there preſent, and Imparted all to <hi>Beatus Rhenanus,</hi> who gave <hi>Luther</hi> much deſerved Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; whereupon, <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf acknowledged,<note place="margin">See <hi>Luther, Tom.</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> page 60.</note> All the Doctors there, in the Doctrine, concerning Grace, and good works, are of my Judgement, yea almoſt the whole Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, the Prince himſelf, and, our Biſhop in Ordinary, and all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56718:14"/>the Ingenious Citizens with one conſent affirme, that before they neither knew, nor heard of the Goſpel, nor of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>After this, <hi>Luther</hi> was ſummoned to <hi>Rome</hi> to maintaine ſome thing which he had written againſt Indulgencies, but <hi>Luther</hi> uſed his beſt endeavours, that the Cauſe might be heard in <hi>Germany</hi> under Competent Judges, and at length he prevailed by the Mediation of the Univerſity of <hi>Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> to the Pope, whereupon it was Determined that the Council ſhould be held at <hi>Auſpurg,</hi> where <hi>Luther</hi> being Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by Cardinal <hi>Thomas Cajetan</hi> to Revoke his Errours which tended only to Diſturb the Peace of the Church; He made Anſwer, <hi>That he could Revoke no Errours, being as yet not Convicted by any Scripture of any, and thereupon did Appeal to the Judgement of the Church;</hi> But the Cardinal obſerving the ſtrength of his Arguments, and Commanding him not to come into his preſence, unleſs he would Recant; <hi>Luther</hi> was inforced to depart, which Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi> took ſo ill, that he wrote unto the Duke of <hi>Saxony, That he would either ſend</hi> Luther <hi>to</hi> Rome, <hi>or Baniſh him out of his Territoryes, and Exhorted him not to Adhere to</hi> Luther's <hi>Defenders, nor ſtain the Illuſtrious Family of which he was Deſcended:</hi> But the Elector Returned Anſwer, <hi>That it was not in his Power to do it, becauſe</hi> Luther <hi>was not Convicted of any Errour, and had done much good Service in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and Offered his Cauſe to Tryal and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this time the Heroical Courage of <hi>Luther</hi> was very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, for when <hi>Luther</hi> came at firſt to <hi>Auſpurg,</hi> he by the Advice of ſuch as the Prince Elector ſent with him, did attend three whole Dayes to have the Emperours Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his ſafety; The Cardinal in the mean time did ſend a Gentleman for <hi>Luther</hi> to come to him, which <hi>Luther</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, untill the Emperour had granted what he deſired, whereat the Gentleman being much offended, ſaid unto Him; <hi>Do you preſume that Prince</hi> Frederick <hi>will take up Armes in your behalf? I deſire it not</hi> (ſaid Luther) <hi>in any wiſe;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Gentleman replyed, <hi>Where then will you abide? Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> made Anſwer, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Cope of Heaven;</hi> whereupon the Gentleman being almoſt amazed at his Confidence, ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56718:14"/>unto Him; <hi>Suppoſe you had got the Pope, and the Cardinalls in your own Power, what would you do with them? I woul</hi> (ſaid Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>give them Honour, and Reverence; but the fall of Popery is already Begun, and I ſhall ſee it Accompliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon theſe Conſiderations, <hi>Luther</hi>'s heart fainted not, and he Appealed from the Pope to the Council; and much about the ſame time the <hi>Bohemians</hi> ſent a Book to <hi>Luther,</hi> which was written by <hi>John Hus,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Incouraged him to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and Patience, and manifeſted that the Divinity which he Taught, was Sound and True, and which in its due time would procure the over throw both of Pope and Popery.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Diſputation</hi> after this was held at <hi>Leipſwich,</hi> a City in <hi>Miſnia,</hi> and Famous ſince, for the memorable Battels that were fought betwixt the Forces of the Emperour, and the Army of the King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> here <hi>Luther</hi> was invited by <hi>John Echius</hi> to a Diſputation; The <hi>Argument,</hi> or Chief <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> was, <hi>Whether the Pope is Head of the Church by Divine Right?</hi> which <hi>Echius</hi> Affirmed, and <hi>Martin Luther</hi> Denyed; The Chief <hi>Argument</hi> of <hi>Echius</hi> was, <hi>That the Church could not be without a Head, ſeeing it was a Body conſiſting of ſeverall Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers;</hi> and the better to Confirm himſelf, he produced the place in <hi>St. Matthew, Thou art Peter,</hi> and ſome Sentences of <hi>St. Jerome,</hi> and <hi>St. Cyprian,</hi> and the Judgement of the Councill of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> in which it was Concluded, <hi>That it was neceſſary to Salvation, that men ſhould believe that the Pope was the Oecomenical Biſhop, or Chriſts Vicar over the whole World;</hi> but <hi>Luther</hi> did Refell his <hi>Arguments</hi> with ſo much Vigour and Acuteneſſe of Spirit, that his Adverſaries were amazed to find him ſo well prepared; After that they entred into Diſputation concerning <hi>Purgatory</hi> and <hi>Indulgencies;</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Remiſſion of ſins,</hi> and the <hi>puniſhment of them,</hi> and concerning the <hi>Power of the Prieſts;</hi> This <hi>Diſputation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt. Tom.</hi> 1 page, 176.</note> was afterwards ſet forth by <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf, to his great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> finding that by ſo many over-throws which he had given to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he had contracted the Envy, and the Hatred of ſeveral Perſons of Eminency, he Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed himſelf in a Letter to <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour, in which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56718:15"/>he Humbly beſought him, <hi>That he would ſo long vouchſafe him his protection as that he might give an account of his proceedings to the World, and either be known to overcome himſelf, or to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by others,</hi> he declared himſelf, <hi>that it would not become his Imperial Majeſty to permit that the Innocent ſhould be violently handled, and be trampled on by their Wicked Adverſaries.</hi> To the ſame Effect he Directed his Letters to the Marquiſes, Earles, and Lords of the Empire; Not long afterwards he did write to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Meniz,</hi> and Repreſented to him how he was Condemned by two ſorts of Men, <hi>By ſome who never did Read his Books</hi> and by Others, <hi>Who had Read them but with hearts full of Hatred and Prejudice;</hi> The Arch Biſhop returned him a Civil Anſwer, <hi>That he heartily Deſired that all matters in Religion ſhould be handled by</hi> Luther, <hi>and all Others, Religiouſly, Reverently and Modeſtly, and without any Envy, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, and Contumely,</hi> to which <hi>Luther</hi> Anſwered, <hi>That if the work be of GOD, it will ſtand firme, and unmoveable, but if it were out of ſiniſter reſpects, it would eaſily lè blown away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope at this time proceeding violently againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> ſome Noble Men of <hi>Germany,</hi> who were of the ſame Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Luther,</hi> did offer him Intertainment, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; Amongſt whom <hi>Sylveſter de Schavenburgen</hi> did write a Letter to him, to deſire him not to depart into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> nor into <hi>France,</hi> or any other Country, but to have recourſe to him, during the time of the Popes Exaſperations and Threatnings, and promiſed that a Troup of <hi>French</hi> Horſe ſhould be ready to attend his ſafely; Hereupon <hi>Luther</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſuming new Courage did admoniſh <hi>Spaletenus</hi> of it in a Letter to this Effect; <hi>I have here ſent you the Letter of the French King Knight</hi> Sylveſter de Schavenburgen,<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt</note> 
                  <hi>and were it not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to you; I do deſire that by a Letter from the Prince, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice may be given to the Cardinal of St. George, whereby he might underſtand. that ſhould they with their Courſes, and their Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings ox pell me from</hi> Wittenbergh, <hi>they ſhould Effect nothing elſe, but make a bad matter much worſe.</hi> For now there are ſuch, and ſo many Princes not only in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> but in the midſt of <hi>Germany,</hi> who both can and will defend me from the threats thundred out againſt me by my Adverſaries. This
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56718:15"/>unleſs God prevent it, will doubtleſs be the iſſue of his mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, concerning myſelf, I am ready to Adventure upon all Dangers, and equally Contemn both the Favour of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Fury of <hi>Rome: Let them Cenſure and Condemn all that I have written to the Fire, I will not be reconciled to them, nor at any time will I joyne with them, but if I can get any fire where I am, I will burn all the Pontifician Law, the ſink of Hereſies, yea I will make no more Addreſſes wherewith the Enemies of the Goſpel, are more and more incenſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> underſtanding that the <hi>Popes Bull</hi> was coming forth againſt him, did publiſh his Book of the <hi>Babilonian Captivity,</hi> and that Indulgences were the wicked tricks of the flattery of <hi>Rome;</hi> He wrote alſo againſt the <hi>Execrable Bull</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> and called the <hi>Pope Antichriſt,</hi> and confirmed the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Articles</hi> cenſured by the <hi>Bull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is remarkable, that <hi>Eraſmus</hi> being promiſed by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates of the Pope, the greateſt favours if he would but write againſt <hi>Luther; Eraſmus</hi> did mildly Anſwer, <hi>That</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>was a man too great for him to write againſt, and that he Learned more from one ſhort page in</hi> Luther, <hi>then from all the Books of</hi> Thomas Aquinas; Nevertheleſs <hi>Eraſmus</hi> being after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards overcome by ſome great perſons to write againſt <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> did perform his Task with much lenity, and candour, although <hi>Luther</hi> could never after afford him any good word, but according to the diſpoſition of his Temper and Complexion would be very hot and violent againſt him, which he alwayes expreſſed, as often as any occaſion was given to make mention of him; And indeed this inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he condemneth in himſelf; <hi>Almoſt all men</hi> (ſaith Luther) <hi>do reprove me for too much eagerneſs; But I am of a mind,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt</hi> page 6.</note> that it is GODS will to have the inventions of men in this manner op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, for I ſee many things in this our Age that are quietly handled to be ſoon forgotten, &amp; no man to regard them; I do not deny but that I am more vehement then is fit, and this is the reaſon why I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies been ſo averſe in ſhowing my ſelf in Publick, but grievous wrongs were done to the word of GOD, and to the Truth thereof;</hi> whereupon it fell out, that had I not been apt by Nature to Vehemency, and Imbittering my ſtile, the very Indignity of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56718:16"/>the matter would have urged a dead and ſtony heart to have written ſharply, how much more my ſelf who am of an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſpirit, and write not a heavy ſtile, Monſters of Men carried me beyond the due temper of Modeſty.</p>
               <p>For the warrant of this ſharpneſs he uſed to alledge the Example of Chriſt, who called the Jews <hi>an Adulterous, and Perverſe Generation, a Generation of Vipers, Hypocrites, Children of the Devil;</hi> he would alſo alleadge the Example of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who calleth them <hi>Doggs, Vain-bablers, Seducers, and Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate;</hi> whereupon <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> who was all Candour and Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and did bear no great good Affection to the Chair of <hi>Rome,</hi> was wont to ſay of <hi>Luther</hi> in regard of the Diſeaſes of this laſt Age of the World. GOD hath ſent them a ſharp Phyſitian; and <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> would ſay of him; <hi>If the Pope and his Prieſts were ſuch as they ſhould be, they would never need a</hi> Luther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> being diſwaded by many of his Friends from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Council that was held at <hi>Wormes</hi> who told him, <hi>That by the burning of his Books he might well gueſs what was the Popes Cenſure concerning himſelf;</hi> He with a Reſolute Courage ſaid, <hi>Theſe diſcouragements are caſt into my way by Satan, who knew that by the profeſſion of the Truth, eſpecially in ſo Illuſtrious a place, his Kingdome would be ſhaken, and indammaged;</hi> It is recorded that the Duke of <hi>Bavariare</hi>'s Jeſter, whether ſuborned by others, or by Accident, it is uncertain, did meet <hi>Martin Luther</hi> at his Entrance into the City of <hi>Worms</hi> with ſuch a Croſs as is accuſtomed to be carried in Funerals, and with a loud voice he ſaid unto him, <hi>Welcome hither, O thou much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of us who ſate in Darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Council <hi>Luther</hi> being demanded of <hi>Ecchius</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Reſolution concerning his Books, he humdly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of the Emperour, and Princes to grant him their Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Attention, which being accorded to, he ſaid, <hi>Of the Books which I have written, ſome of them do tend unto Faith, and Piety, to theſe my Adverſaries, of then ſelves do give ample Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; Should I recant theſe, I may juſtly be cenſured as a wicked man: Others of my Books are againſt the Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>and the foule Corruptions of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>which ſo much doth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56718:16"/>trouble the Chriſtian World, and bringeth ſo much miſchief; Theſe ſhould I revoke, I ſhould confirme their Tyranny; The third ſort of my Books are againſt thoſe perſons who defend the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Cauſe, againſt which I muſt confeſſe I have been very Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, and yet I cannot Recant thoſe Books, unleſſo I will ſet open a gap to the Impudency of many; And unleſſe I be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed by Teſtimony of Scripture, or by Evident Reaſon, I may not I evoke anything which I have Written or Spoken; for I will not in any wiſe wound my Conſcience, I neither can nor will do any thing to the Offence of my Conſcience; This will I ſtand to, and vary from this I may not; GOD Help me,</hi> Amen. <hi>This will I defend, though I was preſently to dye:</hi> Concerning this, he not long afterwards publiſhed this Excellent Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation.</p>
               <p>I Martin Luther, <hi>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Preacher of the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt do profeſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of <hi>Luth. r.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and Believe that Faith alone without Reſpect to our Good Works doth Juſtifie us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore GOD, and that this Article cannot be overthrown by the</hi> Roman Emperour, <hi>or the</hi> Turk, <hi>or the</hi> Tartarian, <hi>or the</hi> Perſian, <hi>nor by the</hi> Pope, <hi>nor all his</hi> Cardinals, Biſhops, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſizers, Monks, Nuns, Kings, Princes, Potentates <hi>of the World, nor all the</hi> Devils <hi>in Hell. This Article will they, nill they, will ſtand, the Gates of Hell cannot prevaile againſt it. The Spirit of GOD doth Dictate this unto me; This is the True Goſpel, For thus the Article in the Mouth of all Chriſtian Children hath it;</hi> I Believe in Jeſus Chriſt Crucified and Dead; <hi>Now no man dyed for our Sins, but</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>the</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> GOD, <hi>the One, and Onely</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> GOD; <hi>I ſay it again and again;</hi> Jeſus, <hi>the One, and Onely</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> GOD, <hi>Redeemed us from our Sins. This is the moſt ſurely Grounded, the moſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubted Doctrine; This the whole Scripture aloud proclaimeth, though the Devils, the Pope, and the World do ſtorme, and burſt with Anger at it; And if Chriſt alone doth take away the ſins of the World, we verily cannot do it with our own Works, and it is impoſſible that I can lay hold on Chriſt, otherwiſe then by Faith. He is never apprehended
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56718:17"/>by my good Works; and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing Faith alone layeth hold on our Redeemer, and not our Works which are but the Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of our Faith; it is a moſt undoubted Truth, that Faith alone before our Works, or without our Works doth this; for it is nothing elſe to be Juſtified, but to be Redeemed from our Sins; Goods works do follow our Faith, as the Effects, and Fruits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. This Doctrine do I Teach, in this will I perſiſt;</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
               <p>Not long before, <hi>Luther</hi> confuted <hi>Nicholas Storke, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Muncer,</hi> and other Phanatick perſons, who called themſelves Prophets, and broaching new Doctrines, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Evangelical Revelations, and Conferences with God himſelf: Theſe were they who denyed the Baptiſme of Infants, and thereby ſowed the ſeed of Anabaptiſme, and were powerfully and Victoriouſly oppoſed by <hi>Luther;</hi> Some few years afterwards, the Anabaptiſts finding <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenbergh</hi> too hot for them, did ſpread themſelves over all <hi>Helvetia,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> and began to broach their Fancies at <hi>Antwerp;</hi> whereupon <hi>Luther</hi> by an Epiſtle full of Chriſtian Direction, did Advertiſe the Reformed Church at <hi>Antwerp</hi> to take heed of ſuch Erronious Spirits,<note place="margin">Luther Tom. <hi>4.</hi> Jen. <hi>p. 461.</hi>
                  </note> who had very much afflicted him. In the ſame Letter, he recited the Impoſtures of falſe Spirits in Popery, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeducing Spirits of the preſent times. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letter he again deſcribed the Erronious Articles of the Tumultuous Spirits at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and clearly opened the Inconſtancy, boldneſs and ſecret Pride, lurking in that profeſſion, and intreating them to abandon the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion concerning Gods Hidden Will, he deſired them to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto, and to follow the neceſſary precepts ſet before them by GOD himſelf in his own word. The Articles of the Anabaptiſts were theſe;
<list>
                     <item>1. That every Man hath the Spririt.</item>
                     <item>2. That the Spirit was nothing elſe but our Reaſon and Underſtanding.</item>
                     <item>3. That every man believeth.</item>
                     <item>4. That there was no place of Torment for men ſoules, but that the Body onely was condemned.</item>
                     <item>5. That every Soul ſhould be ſaved.</item>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:56718:17"/>
                     <item>6. But even by the Law of Nature, we are taught to do good to our Neighbors, as we would they ſhould do unto us, and that this Will in us was Faith.</item>
                     <item>7. That we ſin not againſt the Law, by deſiring any thing, if our Will conſent not to our Deſires and Luſts.</item>
                     <item>8. That he who hath not the Spirit, hath not Sin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wanteth Reaſon, which Reaſon theſe Anabaptiſts do call the Holy Ghoſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> wrote a Letter of Conſolation to <hi>John Heſſius</hi> of <hi>Breſhaw,</hi> to vindicate himſelf from the Scandal raiſed by the Heretick and the Sectaries, and they fighting againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the True Faith. Hitherto (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) <hi>The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute hath been about the Pope, and Purgatory and the like, being all about differences not grounded on the Scriptures; but now we come to more ſerious matters; now we ſhall ſee the Draggon fighting, or rather we ſhall combate with the Draggon,</hi> Michael <hi>being our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in theſe Heavenly Fights. Now when the Draggon doth endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to pull down the third part of the ſtarrs with his Tayle to the Earth; now the Cauſe will call for our ſtrength in Chriſt; now you ſhall ſee what manner of a Warrier, and how ſtrong a Champion Satan is, whom yet we have not tryed, nor have had ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of him; but the Foundation of God, ſtandeth firm, having this Seal, that God knoweth who are his, and in this, let us be confident to prevaile againſt the Gates of Hell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The wicked deſires of ſome of the Reformed Miniſters in <hi>Germany,</hi> and others, who rather then endure the Papiſts, deſired the yoak of the <hi>Turk;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by <hi>Luther. Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt. Jon.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>It is very Remarkable, that ſome Preachers of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches in the difficulty of their times proceeded to that height of Folly, that they deſired, that the <hi>Turk</hi> might come and lay his yoak upon them, which they conceived would be more eaſie then the Burden of the Pope; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paſtors vainly perſwading the People, that Warr was not to be Weighed againſt the <hi>Turk; Luther</hi> at the ſame time, did put forth a Book againſt the <hi>Turk</hi> in the <hi>German</hi> Tongue, the <hi>Turks</hi> being then with a great Army before <hi>Vienna</hi> the chief City of the Empire; In this Book <hi>Luther</hi> ſpake words of Conſolation to the Emperour, and by way of Prophecy did aſſure him; <hi>That the</hi> Turk <hi>ſhould not at that time prevaile againſt that great City,</hi> which ſhortly after, to the great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the Eſtimation of <hi>Luther,</hi> did come to piſſe.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56718:18"/>
               <p>In the Year, One thouſand five hundred and thirty, there was held a Solemn, and a Numerous Aſſemby before the Emperour and the States of the Empire; at which <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cihon</hi> knowing the Rage of the Papiſts, and the Threats of the Emperour did ſeem to be very Solicitous; <hi>Luther</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing notice of it, deſired him to be Reſolute and Secure for the Proteſtant Cauſe, becauſe he was aſſured that it was Juſt and True, and that it was the Cauſe of God and Chriſt, and not ſtained with the leaſt Sin; <hi>If we fall</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) <hi>Chriſt the Lord and the Ruler of the World falleth with us, and ſuppoſe the Cauſe of Chriſt doth fall, I had rather</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) <hi>fall with Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>55.</hi> Pſal. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>then ſtand with</hi> Caeſar, <hi>I intreat you therefore not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Gods promiſes; Caſt thy Care upon the LORD; Have thy Fyes fixed on him, play the Man, let thy Heart be Comforted!</hi> and in the Goſpel of St. <hi>John, Be of good Comfort, for I have overcome the World.</hi> if Chriſt be the Conquerer of the <hi rend="margQuotes">World, why ſhould we fear it, ar if it would overcome us. I extreamly diſlike your exceſſive cares with which you ſay you are conſumed, that theſe Sorrows prevaile ſo much upon you, is not from the Weakneſſe of our Cauſe, but from the Greatneſſe of your Incredulity; for there were more grounds of Fear and of Trepidation in <hi>John Hus</hi> his time, then ours; But grant that there be a great cauſe of Doubt; God who is the Agent and the chief mover in it, is of greater power, for it is not our cauſe but his; Why then do you afflict your ſelf? If the cauſe be faulty, let us revoke it; but if it be good, why do we make God a Lyer, who hath made us ſo great promiſes?</hi> ſaying, <hi>Caſt thy Care upon the Lord, the Lord is near unto all, who being of a troubled Heart do call upon him;</hi> Is it poſſible for you to effect any thing with your unprofitable Fears and Jeloufies, I pray you tell me; What can the Devill do more unto us then kill us? I beſeech you, ſeeing in all other things you are a good Chriſtian Souldier,<note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of <hi>Luther.</hi>
                  </note> that you would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to overcome your ſelf as being your ſelf your Greateſt Enemy, nor proſide any Armour to arme Satan againg your ſelf, Chriſt dyed once for ſin, but for a Juſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56718:18"/>and true Cauſe he ſhall never dye, but live and reign in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. Tell me then what fear is there for the truth, if Chriſt reign; if it be caſt down by the wrath of God, let us be caſt down with it, but let it not be done by our ſelves. He who is become our father, will become the father of all thoſe that put their truſt in him. God is able to raiſe the Dead. He is powerfull to maintain his own Cauſe ready to fall, yea to raiſe it again if it were fallen, and to promote and advance it as it now ſubſiſteth. If he think us unworthy to be his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſo great a work, let it be done by others. And if we be not intreſted in his promiſes, I pray you, who are they in the world whom they belong unto?</p>
               <p>The Proteſtants Confeſſion was afterwards cheerfully ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoxy, George</hi> Marquis of <hi>Braxde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Erneſtus</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> and <hi>Francis</hi> Duke of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenburgh, Philip Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Haſſia,</hi> and <hi>Wolfgany</hi> Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> ſuch great and eminent perſons had the Goſpel in a ſhort time procured to maintain the purity thereof, it was alſo acknowledged and ſubſcribed to, by two Imperial Cities, the City of <hi>Norimburgh,</hi> and the City of <hi>Reutlin,</hi> the papiſts were commanded to confute it if they could, which confutation was at the laſt drawn up and ingroſſed, and preſented to the Emperour, but a Copy of it being not to be procured, but upon conditions that it ſhould not be publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor tranſcribed, nor any Reply made thereunto, the Marquiſs of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Emporour that he would permit them to take a friendly courſe for the compoſing of the Controverſy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luther</hi> as well the great Instrument as the great Prophet of the Downfall of the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> which accordingly was granted, and of each party there were ſeven Arbitrators choſen who were to provide for the eſtabliſhment of a political peace. In which when the proteſtant party ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to condeſcend too much unto the papiſts, <hi>Luther</hi> who was ordained the ſcourge of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to be as well the Inſtrument as the prophet of his downfall, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thoſe who were Arbitrators for the proteſtants to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circumſpect in what they gave unto the papiſts, for ſaid he, they will take our grants in the large, in the larger, and in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56718:19"/>the larger ſence and will exhibite and interpret their own in a ſtrict, in a ſtricter nay in the ſtricteſt ſence that poſſibly they can; In breif ſaid <hi>Luther,</hi> I diſlike this Arbitration for an agreement betwixt the Papiſts and proteſtants in point of Doctrine, as being a thing utterly impoſſible, unleſſe the Pope will aboliſh his Popedome: Chriſt is come, and raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, let the Devils if they will, turn Monkes, and Nuns, nor doth any ſhape better become them, then that in which they have hitherto ſet forth themſelves to be adored by the world.</p>
               <p>But the Iſſue of the Arbitration came to this, that although the Proteſtants deſired peace of <hi>Caſar,</hi> yet their petition could not be granted and a war was threatened or baniſhment to fall on thoſe who would not be obedient to the Decrees of <hi>Caſar</hi> wherefore <hi>Luther</hi> with an undaunted ſpirit did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a Book to the whole nation of <hi>Germany</hi> in the <hi>German</hi> tongue, in which he ſhowed them that they ought not to obey a wicked Edict, or by armes be aſſiſtant to the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the true Doctrine of the Goſpell, nor fight for I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols and other abominations of the Papiſts. Howſoever he did adviſe the proteſtants not to take up Armes before the Popiſh party under the Emperour ſhould invade them with war, but if they then ſhould reſiſt their enemies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves by force of Armes, he ſaid, they were to be excuſed, ſo long as they ſtood upon their Deſence and maintain the Truth of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In the mean time diverſe of the Proteſtants were baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to whom <hi>Luther</hi> directed a letter to comfort them in their baniſhment, and adviſed them chearfully to undergo their preſent calamity and to give God thanks who indued them with patience, and who alſo vouchſafed them courage and conſtancy. He acquainted them that this triumphing of their Adverſaries was neither ſound nor laſting, and that it would periſh ſooner then they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined; He found (he ſaid) that all the attempts of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Goſpell were hitherto fruſtrated, and by the ſingular mercy of God fallen to the ground.</p>
               <p>In the year one thouſand five hundred thirty and ſeven
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56718:19"/>the Pope pretended a ſerious reformation of abuſes crept into the Church; The meeting was at <hi>Vintcentia</hi> (a large and renowned City of the <hi>Venetians</hi>) at which time <hi>Luther</hi> publiſhed another book in anſwer to the Popiſh reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The picture in the frontis-peice of his book did ſhow the Argument of it, for he repreſented the Pope ſitting in a high throne, with many Cardinals round about him, the Cardinals carried in their hands long poles, on the tops whereof they had faſtened great Fox-tails, with which as with ſo many bruſhes they endeavoured to cleanſe all parts on both ſides of them, and every corner about them and beneath them.</p>
               <p>Here, as if the Church had not contentions enough al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, the ſect of the <hi>Antinomians</hi> ſtartled up; They held that repentance was not to be taught by the ten comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and they diſputed againſt thoſe Divines who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that the Goſpell was not to be taught to any, but to ſuch as were humbled by the law. And themſelves held that whatſoever a mans life was, though never ſo impure, yet he was juſtified if lie verily beleived the Goſpel. <hi>Luther</hi> who wraſtled with the Papiſts at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in <hi>Germany</hi> and gave them many falls, untill the heartſtrings of their Religion crack'd again, did willingly enter into the liſts with them, and did eaſily throw them on their backs, He ſhowed that the law was not given that we might be juſtified by it, but to ſhow us our ſins, and to terify our Conſciences, The law was therefore firſt to be taught and the Goſpel afterwards, which ſheweth us our Mediator Jeſus Chriſt bleſſed for evermore.</p>
               <p>Much about this time, or not long afterwards it was that <hi>Luther</hi> compoſed a Treatiſe, concerning a defence of this Reformed Church lawfully, approved, and not contrary to Gods will, and now becauſe the Names of this Councill and of the Church were in every mans mouth,<note place="margin">How the Pope doth play with the Church of Chriſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Luther</hi> did publiſh a Book in the <hi>Cerman</hi> tongue concerning both of them, in the preface whereof he ſaith that the pope by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Council, doth play with the Church of Chriſt as they do with a Dogge who offer him a cruſt of bread on the poynt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56718:20"/>of a knife, and when the Dogge doth put his head forth to take it, they knock him on the noſe with the haft of the knife to procure laughter in thoſe who do behold it.</p>
               <p>In the year one thouſand five hundred forty and two <hi>Luther</hi> publiſhed ſomething in relation to the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran</hi> which was tranſlated into the <hi>German</hi> toungue by one <hi>Richard</hi> a <hi>Dominican Frier</hi> to which <hi>Luther</hi> added a faithfull admonition concerning the abandoning of the Turks Doctrine; and affirmed that not the Turk but the popre was <hi>Amichriſt,</hi> and upon a diffirence between the Elector of Saxony, and prince <hi>Monurice</hi> concerning the teritoryes, and City of <hi>worcen, Luther</hi> with weighty reaſons diſſwaded both princes form there deſignes; he alſo further declared himſelf concerning a poſition propounded by him in reference to the warre againſt the Turk, for <hi>Luther</hi> foreſaw that to puniſh the ſins of the <hi>Cermans</hi> the Turks in due proceſſe of Time ſhould make formidable and fortunate Incurſions into the Empier of <hi>Germany,</hi> to the Ruine thereof, which made him to prophecy, that upon ſuch accounts to make war againſt the Turk, was nothing elſe but to fight againſt God who doth uſe him as his whip to ſcourge them for there; ſins he therefore much lamented many great perſonages of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> who ſought obſtinately to opreſſe this Goſpell,<note place="margin">To make againſt the Turk is to to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God who maketh the Turk his ſcour gets puniſh the German Nation.</note> for which they muſt expect ſevere puniſhments to fall upon them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> ſet forth a forme of publick prayer and Communion wherein he retained all the uſuall Rites which were not plainly repugnant to the word of God, as his preface out of the pſalnes, the Confeſſion, the Collect, the Epiſtle and Goſpell, the Creed, the prayers, the Lords prayer, the words of the Lords ſupper the thanks-giving &amp;c: This was the firſt chance of the Rites in the Church though attempted before by <hi>Caroloſtadius</hi> and when two Monks of the profeſſion of the <hi>Auguſtins</hi> were taken by the Inquiſition and burned for neglecting the old forme,<note place="margin">The monks and Nuns began to fall from the Pope.</note> being the firſt that ſhed their bloud for the reformed Doctrine for the Faith, <hi>Luther</hi> renowned their Conſtancy with a Hymne or Pſalms, and extolled them as the firſt Martyrs
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56718:20"/>of his time, of which <hi>Eraſmuſs Roterodamus</hi> alſo maketh mention, thus both Morks and Nuns began to fall from the pope; many monkes, at this time began to abondon there monaſtaries being, Illuminated with the bright rayes of the Goſpell, which now began to ſhine forth in perfect <hi>Luſters,</hi> to whom <hi>Martin Luther</hi> ſent Letters aſ conſolation as alſo to the three noble Virgins of <hi>Friburg</hi> other Nuns alſo left their cloyſters elſewhere; whereupon <hi>Luther</hi> wrote thus to <hi>Spalatinus,</hi> there came to me nine converted Nuns who left the monaſtrey of <hi>Nimpſchen</hi> they were conducted by h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſt Citizens I much pity them and many others like unto them who every where in great number periſh by their accurſed and inceſtuous Chaſtity.</p>
               <p>The ſacrifices of the maſſe did now begin to be every where cryed down; the <hi>Emperour</hi> indeavored to make a decree to ſuppreſſe the growth of the proteſtant Religion but all in vain, for this buſines was far beter concluded of in Heaven t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Norimberg,</hi> and the princes and cheife Cityes of the <hi>Empire</hi> ſtrove who firſt ſhould intertain the Reformed Doctrine.</p>
               <p>The maſſe (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) muſt undoubtedly fall, Three yeares ſince here was a <hi>Moorean</hi> who ſhewed me for certayn that in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and all the Eaſtern Countries (where are many aſſemblies of the Chriſtians) there is no celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the maſſe at all, and although that in <hi>Italy</hi> there are many who are much addicted to my Doctrine which would find a good party there, were I not ſo violent againſt the Idolatry of the maſſe, yet it finds a great Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enes in <hi>France,</hi> and other Countryes and undoubtedly it will fall with Popery it ſelf (as being a great pillar of it) as God in the bright Rayes of his Goſpel ſhall ſhine upon the heart, and rectify the underſtandings of the poor deluded people.</p>
               <p>The Head of Antichriſt is the Pope, and the Turk and as every living Beaſt muſt have a ſoul and a body,<note place="margin">The Head of Antichriſt is the pope <hi>298</hi>
                  </note> ſo the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and ſoul of Antichriſt is the Pope, and the body is the Turk. The Turk is the battle axe and ſcourge of God (as I have already ſaid) he cometh to execute vengeance upon
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56718:21"/>thoſe who prophane his holy name, and do deſtroy the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſometimes did) who being Gods Inſtrument God in the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is pleaſed to call him his ſervant. <hi>The</hi> Pope deſtroyeth the Church of God ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, yea, and corporally too, with hanging, murdering and with burning. And as in the Apoſtles time, the Church had, and kept the victory, ſo it ſhall at this day main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and keep the Feild againſt the Hypocriſie, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Pope, and Turk, and againſt the power of all Enemies whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>Luthers</hi> expounding the Prophecy of the Prophet <hi>Daniel.</hi> chap. <hi>II.</hi> concerning <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd He ſhall do according to his will, and he ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt himſelf, and magnify himſelf above every God, and ſhall ſpeak mervailous things againſt the God of Gods, and ſhall proſper till the Indignation be accompliſhed, for what is determined ſhall be done; Neither ſhall he regard the God of his Fathers, nor the deſire of women, nor any God for he ſhall magnify himſelf above All.</p>
               <p>This prophecy (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) as all Teachers do inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret doth point directly at <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth God, nor the love of women, that is the ſtate of <hi>Matrimony Antichriſt</hi> ſhall condemn theſe two on Earth, Firſt <hi>God,</hi> that is Religion, and ſecondly woman, he will contemn all the laws of Wedlock, all houſe government, for by women Children are begotten, and brought up to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Humane ſociety, and the repleniſhing of the world, therefore when that ſhall be diſregarded, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, then of neceſſity all the conjunction of politicall government which eſtabliſhed in the laws of Matrimony muſt fall with it, nay Kings and Emperours, and all their laws and Ordinances muſt fall to the ground with it.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:56718:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) was ſo high a Prophet, that Chirſt eſpecially loved him, and of whom he ſaid, who ſo readeth him let him mark; He ſpake ſo clearly of that <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Horror, as if he had been at that time an Eye witneſſe of it, Read Chapter II. throughout.</p>
               <p>He ſaith in expreſſe words,<note place="margin">The Pope directly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt page <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall plant the Tabernacle of his palace between the Seas upon the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Holy Mount, that is to ſay, at <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi> The Turk alſo doth rule over the two Seas at <hi>Constantinople</hi> but he doth not ſtrengthen nor advance the worſhiping of <hi>Maoſim</hi> neither doth the Turk prohibite matrimony, but offendeth in the contrary by his polygamy, which is by permitting too many mariages to one perſon. Therefore in this text <hi>Daniel</hi> pointeth directly at the Pope who doth accompliſh both with great eagerneſs, and ſecurity.</p>
               <p>The prophet ſaith further, He ſhall be forſaken of his Lord which is allready come to paſſe, (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>), ſince Kings and Princes do leave him; I do adviſe therefore (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) that in any caſe we ſhould do it for moſt ſure and certain that the Pope is the true <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As concerning the manner of the Religion betwixt the Turk and the Pope there is no great difference, but only in Ceremonies. The Turk obſerveth the Moſaicall, but the Pope the Chriſtian Ceremonies, yet both of them do falſify and ſophiſticate in their Ceremonies; for as the Turk doth force and defile the Moſaical waſhings and bathings even ſo the Pope ſtaineth the right uſe of Baptiſme, and of the Sacrament of the Altar.</p>
               <p>In the like manner the Pope ſhall be deſtroyed without hands and ſhall die in himſelf, for he began his Kingdome in Superſtition, and external ſhinings and the prerended Authority of Scripture; This is the ground on which Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is builded, and through which it is fallen and every day will fall more and more. It is therefore ſpoken in the Prophecy of <hi>Daniel</hi> that he ſhall be broken without hands, and this aymeth directly at the Pope, for all other Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and Monarchs do uſe Temporall power, and ſtrength.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56718:22"/>
               <p>But why (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) doth the Pope name himſelf an Earthly God, as though the true onely, and Almighty God in Heaven were not alſo a God on Earth. Truly (ſaith <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>) The Popes Kingdome is a horrible wrath of God, an abomination of deſſolation which ſtandeth in the Holy place, as Chriſt ſpeaking directly of it ſaith, <hi>Who ſo reddeth let him underſtand. Mat.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>It muſt indeed be a great wrath of God, that a humane Creature dares preſume (Chriſt being come and revealed in the fleſh) to exalt himſelf in the throne of God, if it had been done amongſt the <hi>Gentiles</hi> before the comming of Chriſt it had not been ſo great a wonder, And although the Trophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and St <hi>Peter,</hi> and Chriſt himſelf have given us warning of this Beaſt, yet we Chriſtians have been ſtill ſo fooliſh, as to adore and worſhip all his Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and to believe that he is a Lord over the univerſall world under the Name and title of the ſucceſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when as neither <hi>Peter</hi> nor Chriſt himſelf left any Dominion pon Earth.</p>
               <p>To conclude, the Pope is the laſt blaze in the lamp which ere it be long will go out, and be extinguiſhed, He is the laſt Inſtrument of darkneſs, who lighteneth, and thundreth with ſword and Bull, who maketh and maintaineth war through the power and the ſtrength of others. It hath here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore been, ſaid, The Pope in one finger hath more power then all the princes in <hi>Germany,</hi> but he beginneth now to be no more regarded. <hi>He is powerfull but not in his own ſtrength</hi> (ſaith <hi>Daniel.</hi>) He beginneth every day to loſe his eſtimation which no Emperour with ſword and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had been able to accompliſh; when he is ſtruck with Gods word, the Pope is turned to a puppet. But who is he (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) who about thirty years ago durſt ſo much, as to have had ſuch a thought of the Pope, for in thoſe dayes the Pope would have caſt whom he pleaſed head long into hell, let him fetch himſelf out again, as well as he could.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:56718:22"/>
               <p>The pope,<note place="margin">The horrible inſolence of the Pope page <hi>301.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) hath done his worſt and although he falleth not all together, yet every day he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe more and more. He boaſteth in his decretals that he hath power and Authority over all Rule and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both in Heaven and Earth, and that he is a Lord over all Lords. How dares any humane Creature ſpeak in this manner, ſurely, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> neither God nor King can indure it. He muſt undoubtedly fall, His Tyranny hath climbed up too high, he hath preſumed to tread Kings and Emperors under his feet, with ſuch powerfull errours God hath ſo blinded the world untill the Indignation be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
               <p>Any thing is lawfull at <hi>Rome,</hi> In <hi>England</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) was a Cardinall (Cardinall <hi>Woolſy</hi> I beleive) who was the ſon of a Butcher, concerning whom a merry perſon ſaid, God be prayſed we have got ſuch a Cardinall, who when he commeth to be Pope we may cat fleſh freely in lent, and on other forbidden days, for St. Peter being a fiſher he forbade eating of fleſh to the end that he might ſell his fiſh at a higher rate, but this Cardinall being a Butchers ſon will he give us a diſpenſation for fleſh to gain more mony thereby, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> cauſed two Cityes to be painted on his table the one was the City in which he was born, the other was the City of <hi>Lovain</hi> where he commenced Maſter of Arts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 305.</note> neer unto the ſide of the City of his Nativity he wrote theſe words, <hi>I have planted,</hi> and cloſe by the other, he wrote theſe words, <hi>I have wattered;</hi> under the two Cityes the <hi>Emperour</hi> was pictured with theſe words, but J gave the bleſſing thereunto; whereupon another wrote underneath, <hi>God did nothing heer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed what may be expected from a place where God is not, but ruin, and confuſion, and utter deſolation. The Pope is full of hell and damnation, as the promiſes of God are full of mercy;<note place="margin">How the Pope doth play with the Church of Chriſt.</note> we ought not to doubt (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) nor to diſpair of ſuch a ſinner that repenteth, and is ſorry for his ſins and confeſſeth them, and deſireth forgivenes for them, allthough he ſall continually into ſin again. But we muſt have reguard unto this, that if ſuch a one dyeth in his ſin then his caſe is doubtfull, and dangerous, In the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56718:23"/>yeere 1539 on the eighth day of <hi>January,</hi> a Comet was ſeen at <hi>Wittenbergh</hi> about ſix of the Clock in the evening; it ſhot its threantning trayn from the <hi>Weſt</hi> to the <hi>North,</hi> and towards che <hi>Eaſt.</hi> The comet was beheld by <hi>Philip Melanncthon,</hi> by <hi>Inſtus Ionas,</hi> and <hi>Martin Luther</hi> and others; Whereupon <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, I will prophecy over <hi>Germany,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luthers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. <hi>522.</hi>
                  </note> not out of the planets, or this dreadful comet but I will decare unto her the Anger of God, out of his own word for it is impoſſible that <hi>Germany</hi> ſhould eſcape unpuniſhed, ſhe muſt recive a great ſcourge there is no remedy, for God is daily prouoked to deſtroy her, the Godly with the ungodly muſt be viſited and both of them taſt of the rod. <hi>Germany</hi> is like unto a gallant horſe that is high of mettall, and well fed, but wanteth a good rider, now, as aſtrong and fiery horſe will not obey the bridle but driveth on forward, and beares down all before him, except he hath an expecienced rider to command him, ſo for want of a head and good governour <hi>Germany</hi> will betray her ſelf, and leave her ſelf open to the Incurſions of her Eni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nyes the Turks who in formidable numbers will come in like a deluge upon them to overwhelm them.</p>
               <p>And ancient Miniſter who ſupped with <hi>Lnther,</hi> ſpake all the tiwe he was at ſupper very much of Rome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Luther</hi> demaunded of him how often he had bin there, he anſwrered foure times, and why ſo often ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> he replyed, firſt I ſought a knave there, at my ſecond iourny to Rome I found him, on my third iourney I brought him from thence and in my laſt iourney I carryed him thither again, and placed him behind <hi>Saint Peters</hi> Altar.</p>
               <p>We find God rejected the Nation of the Iewes, becavſe they reſuſed to hearken to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the prophets, nor would receive them, inſomuch the ſame was ueriſyed of them of which the prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeakteh: Chap: 9. The people turneth not unto him that ſmiteth them, neyther doe they ſeek the Lord of hoſts, Therefore the Lord will cut off from <hi>Iſrael</hi> head, and tayle, branch and root in one day. Even thus (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) they were diperſed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56718:23"/>accordingly towards the Eaſt, towards the Weſt, and the South, All Hiſtories do ſhew that by God they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, and now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o live without Chriſt and Comfort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they gave ſo little a regard to the prophecies,<note place="margin">The Germans for their ſins to be diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as the Jews page. <hi>535.</hi>
                  </note> and Doctrine of the Prophets, and the Apoſtles. Even ſo will it go with Us <hi>Germans</hi> likewiſe, who now at laſt are called, and invited to the ſupper of the All-ſaving Goſpel, becauſe we acknowledge not the time of our Viſitation. God of his infinite mercy preſerve us from the ſame, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas I fear the Goſpel will too too ſoon be removed from us <hi>Germans,</hi> for how ſhould peace, and quiet, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be there, where licentiousneſs, and prophaneneſs raineth, and vvhere all are mortall Enemies to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Turkiſh preparations.</head>
               <p>LEt us truly repent (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) let us pray, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the will of God, for Humane Help and Aſſiſtance is too weak. Some years ſince, the Emperour was well able to reſiſt the Turk, and to make a war upon them, but then he would not, and therefore many good people as ſheep in the ſhambles were lamentably butchered, and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the Turks, I fear all things go not right,<note place="margin">The Turks proclamtion this prophecy came to paſſe this laſt yeare.</note> for our own pride and tyranny will give us over to the Turks and make us ſubject to them.</p>
               <p>If the Turk ſhall cauſe Proclamation to be made that every man ſhall be free from Taxations and tributes for the ſpace of three years, then the common people with joy will ſurrender themſelves unto him; But when he hath once
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56718:24"/>gotten them into his clawes he will then make uſe of his tyranny, as his cuſtome is, for he taketh the third ſon from every man; He is always the Father of the third Child. Truly this is a great tyranny which cheifly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the Princes of the Empire themſelves. I ever held the Emperour ſuſpected, he can deeply diſſemble. Let us call upon God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let us pray, it is high time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperour was in a manner captivated by the Pope and Papiſts, they had him in their power, and he was conſtrained to do what they pleaſed, he was compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by them to put on, and to wear a Deacons coat, and in Chriſt-maſs Holidays to read the Goſpel to the Pope, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that every Emperour ſince is a Deacon of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church, and the King of the <hi>Romans</hi> is a Sub-deacon, and he is to read the Epiſtle before the Pope, ſo that the Emperour and the King are both the Popes Maſs-ſervants.<note place="margin">This is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable Luthers page: <hi>412</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperour after he had performed this Ceremony to the Pope had never any good ſucceſs againſt the Turks in <hi>Germany,</hi> the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> is fallen which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a very fair Kingdome.</p>
               <p>This is the ſum of <hi>Luthers</hi> Prophecies in relation to the Downfall of the Pope, and of the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> I ſhall conclude with his prophecy on himſelf which is in theſe words. Thoſe who in my life do reſuſe the kernell of my Doctrine, will after my death be glad to enjoy the ſhell if they can get it. Let every one in time prepare himſelf to reap whiles it is yet harveſt, for as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that followeth me ſhall not walk in darkneſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> was often heard to deplore the ungodly Invocation, or praying unto Saints departed, and ſaid, There were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Reaſons why that Invocation was execreable, and this was one, namely that by that prophane Cuſtome, the Teſtimony of Chriſts Divinity was obſcured to whom alone the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles attribute the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56718:24"/>Honor of invocation.<note place="margin">Invocation of Saints the Idol that whetteth the barbarous ſword of the Turk to cut our throats. <hi>Melanthon, Tom. 6.</hi>
                  </note> Theſe are the Idols which ſharpen the barbarous ſword of the Turk to cut our throats except in a more ſpeedy and Godly manner theſe things be reformed, for how wicked and how impious are theſe Hymus which are dayly ſung in the popes Chappell. <hi>O Mary thou Mother of Grace, defend us from our Enemyes, and in the hour of Death receive us: And theſe Hymnes, Saint Dorothy create a new Heart within us, and Saint Catherine tranſlate us from the troubleſome ſea of this world to the pleaſure of paradiſe. Open paradiſe for us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It being brought to <hi>Luthers</hi> eare how much the Goſpell began to flouriſh for all the malicc of the Pope and the vain indeavours of the princes to ſuppreſs it, and that the Papiſts, and the Emperor himſelf were ſo violent againſt him that they ſought to take away his life, I had rather ſaid <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> dye by the hands of the Pope, and would by no means, (if I could help it) that the Emperour or any of his Counſellors ſhould interpoſe themſelves in putting me to death. I know what miſery befell the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> after the Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>John Hus</hi> at <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and that nothing proſpered after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with him, how he dyed without Iſſue Male, and how his daughters Son <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> alſo dyed, and how in one Age he had his Name quite extinguiſhed, and how his Empreſs <hi>Barbara</hi> by name, became a diſhonour to the Royal Throne: That Kings and Princes rage againſt Chriſt or the Anointed of God I eſteem it as a good ſign, and think it much better then if they flattered, for thereupon it comes to paſs that he that dwelleth in Heaven laugheth them to ſcorn, And when our Lord and King laughes, I ſee no reaſon that we ſhould weep before their faces, he laugheth not for his own ſake but for ours, that we truſting in him, and nothing elſe, might laugh at their vain Deſignes, ſo much need is there of Faith, that the Cauſe of Faith may not be looked upon without Faith. It was he vvho began this work of Refotmation without our Contrivance or our Counſell,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56718:25"/>and he himſelf will advance it and accompliſh it without our Aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>The Pope (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) makes uſe of the Maſs even for ſouls departed, He hath gone with his Maſſe not onely into all Corners of the World,<note place="margin">The Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be taken by the Turk pag. <hi>378.</hi>
                  </note> but even into purgatory it ſelf. His Indulgence-Mongers are his purſe thraſhers and he winnoweth good mony out of that chaffe, moſt excellent is the ſpeech and prophecy of the Reverend and learned <hi>Muſculus</hi> which, to conclude this Diſcourſe I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite to you in his own words <hi>Magnis Indulgentiis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arceuerunt Inſinitos theſauros praetextu fabricarum Eccleſias ticarum preſertim, ſancti Petri, quae ſic aediſicatur</hi> Romae <hi>ut ad plenum aedificata ſit nunquam, citiuſque deſtruenda ſit a Turcis quam ad finem structurae perducenda a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With great Indulgences they have amaſſed into one Banke infinite ſummes of money under the pretence of the building of Churches; eſpecially the Church of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> which is ſo builded at <hi>Rome,</hi> that it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be fully finiſhed, and vvill ſooner be deſtroyed by the Turks, then be brought by the <hi>Romans</hi> to the perfection of its ſtructure.</p>
               <p>It is obſerveable that the late Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> who was beheaded on <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> having heard of the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on of this Book of <hi>Luther</hi> into the <hi>Engliſh tongue,</hi> had a great deſire to ſee it in the manuſcript, and it being ſent unto him, he ſome few dayes afterwards commanded his Chaplin Doctor <hi>Bray</hi> to give the Gentleman a Viſit, and to acquaint him that he had never read a more excellent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine work which was worthy of eternal Memory; At that time he ſent the Gentleman that tranſlated it ten pound in gold, And about a year afterwards having had the leiſure fully to peruſe the work he returned it back with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56718:25"/>this Approbation, that he would make known unto his Majeſty what an excellent work he had rendred into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and that he would have it printed and diſperſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Kingdome,<note place="margin">Luther. Col. loq. ment in the Epiſtle Dedicatory.</note> And in token of his reſpect unto the Gentleman he preſented him at that time with forty pound in gold, by the ſame Chaplain whom before he had ſent unto him.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
